In 1915,
一九一五年
World War I entered its second year of unprecedented tragedy.
第一次世界大战进入空前惨烈的第二年
Yuan Shikai's vain attempt to restore the monarchy
袁世凯妄想复辟帝制的企图
also gradually resurfaced.
也逐渐浮出水面
Domestic and foreign troubles have once again thrown China into turmoil.
内忧外患将中国再次抛于风雨飘摇之中
Twice in three years!
三年之内两度复辟
Zhongfu, get rid of your illusions and be ready to fight.
仲甫兄啊丢掉幻想准备战斗吧
We need to complete a great change that has not been seen in three thousand years,
我们要完成三千年未遇之大变局
defeat a powerful enemy that has not been met in three thousand years.
要战胜三千年未遇之大强敌
Each generation has their duty.
一代人有一代人的责任
I'd like to invite you to Peking University as a liberal arts student,
我想请你到北大担任文科学长
and give the university a helping hand.
助北大一臂之力
With the efforts of all our colleagues,
在各位同仁的努力下
our "New Youth" magazine has already accomplished in becoming
我们《新青年》杂志已经成为了
the most influential publication in China.
中国最有影响力的刊物
We should use new ideas,
要用新思想
new culture,
新文化
new ethics,
新伦理
to arm the minds of our members,
来武装我们会员的头脑
improve their conduct,
改良我们会员的品行
advance their knowledge.
进步我们会员的学问
This is also the first and only mission of our Xinmin Society.
这也是我们新民学会的初衷和使命
Call on the masses of patriotic youth to consciously
号召广大爱国青年自觉地
transform their thinking.
把改造自身思想
Combine social transformation
司改造社会结合起来
with the fundamental transformation of Chinese society.
实现对中国社会的根本改造
We advocate new culture:
我们倡导新文化
this is to seek liberation in all aspects.
就是要谋求各个方面的解放
Our golden world,
我们黄金的世界
our splendid world,
我们光华灿烂的世界
is right in front of us!
就在眼前
Use your journalist status
利用你的记者身份
to get some people to write articles
找些人写文章
directly aimed at Chen Duxiu and Cai Yuanpei.
直接对准陈独秀蔡元培
Make a big deal out of it. Make him look bad.
大造典论把他搞臭
Chen Duxiu! Hypocrite!
陈独秀伪君子
Chen Duxiu! You don't deserve to be a teacher!
陈独秀你不配为人师表
If we don't fight back,
如果我们不奋起反击
the torch of new culture will be put out.
新文化的火炬就必然被扑灭
I will write another novel.
我会再写一部小说
I will compete with Lin Qinnan!
我就要跟这个林琴南较个高低
This debate over culture is just and dignified.
文化之争堂堂正正
This is not natural!
如此下作非士之所为
How could you think of that?
亏你们想得出来
I know you won't do anything to harm the people.
我知道你不会去做祸害老百姓的事
We can't let people poke us in the back, can we?
咱不能让人家戳咱脊梁骨是吧
I don't think people can live for themselves.
我觉得人不能为了自己而活着
Go to Changxin
你到长辛店
and take a look at the ruined shanties.
去看看那些破败不堪的工棚
Go to Jinpu and take a look at them:
你去津浦线去看看那些
refugees with thousands of hungry people.
饿孕千里的难民
Go to Qianmen Street
你再去前门大街
and go see the the beggars begging along the street.
去看看那些沿街气讨的气正
Shouldn't we do something for them?
我们难道不该为他们于点什么吗
Are you asking us to be like you?
你难道要求我们像你一样
Clean and shiny?
光鲜亮丽地活着吗
Two proposals from your delegation,
贵代表团所提两项提案
none of them are in the authority of the peace conference.
均不在和会权限之内
The Shandong Peninsula
山东半岛
is not in the interests of China and Germany
不是中国和德国的利益
but in the interets of Japan and Germany.
而是日本和德国的利益
Didn't we win?
我们不是打赢了吗
Germany was defeated!
德国打败了
Qingdao should be returned!
青岛该收回来了
In defeat, one bides their time.
打败了要忍
We shouldn't have to put up with powers anymore!
打胜了还要忍
Weak countries get pushed around. This is the law of the world.
弱国无外交这是铁律
China is our Chinese people's China.
中国是我们中国人的中国
If we do not love our country,
我们自己的国家
who will love it?
我们不爱谁爱
Yeah!
对
The country is at its tipping point in time.
国家到了这个时候
We have to fight hard.
我们唯有奋力一搏
"Life and death for the country.
苟利国家生死以
Is it because of fortune or misfortune?"
岂因祸福避趋之
Do you think
你们以为
waking one up
唤醒一个
from feudal thought
被封建思想
in a nation imprisoned for thousands of years
禁了几千年的民族
is that easy?
是那么容易的吗
Do you think
你们以为
removing numbness, indifference
要扫除我们这个民族
and outdated thinking
血液里面的麻木冷漠
from our nation's blood,
愉性思维
is achieved in a day?
是一日之功吗
Once a man's mind is awakened,
人的思想一旦觉悟了
the old order loses its foundation.
日的统治就失去了根基
I was a young man,
我是一个年轻时候
a revolutionary who was determined to save the country.
就立志救国的革命者
put myself in a position to die first.
要先让自己置之死地而后生
I have to fight with them
我必须要跟他们在一起去战斗
because I love this country.
因为我爱这个国家
I will do something for this country.
我要为这个国家去做点什么
I do it for them,
我为了他们
for them to be able to speak like a human being,
能够像人一样的活着
to have the rights of a human being,
为了他们能够拥有人的权利
to be happy,
人的快乐
to be dignified.
人的尊严
China is a people's country.
中国是人民的国家
Thus the people should be in charge
所以家就应该人民来当
and become their own masters.
主就应该人民来做
This is what a country should do.
这是国家应有之义
The founding of the Communist Party of China:
中国共产党的成立
it's not just
绝不仅仅是
the awakening of our intellectuals.
我们几个知识分子的觉醒
It is, above all, the awakening of the Chinese working class.
它首先是中国工人阶级的觉醒
It is the awakening of all Chinese people.
是全体中国人民的觉醒
It is the great awakening of the Chinese nation.
是中华民族伟大的觉醒
The Communist Party of China represents
中国共产党代表的是
the fundamental interests of the overwhelming majority of the people.
最广大人民群众的根本利益
This is the rational and scientific nature of our Party today,
这才是我们这个党
and the fundamental driving force
今天成立的合理性和科学性
of the Communist Party of China,
更是中国共产党
which is vibrant and unstoppable.
生机勃勃一往无前的根本动力
China must take the socialist road.
中国只有走社会主义道路
Only then can it be realized:
它才能够实现
the rejuvenation of the Chinese nation.
中华民族之振兴
Socialism will never fail China!
社会主义绝不会辜负中国